《莫斯科绅士》
第一季 第1集
1917年革命
处决沙皇贵族
俄国一夜之间改头换面
随后四年布尔什维克主义者重建国家
推翻沙皇贵族统治
俄国将属于人民
政权交替 去旧迎新
不要 求求你
No. Please.
放手 求求你们
Stop! Pleasel
说出你的姓名
State your name.
亚历山大·伊里奇·罗斯托夫
Alexander Ilyich Rostov.
你的住址
Address?
过去四年 我一直住在
For the last four years, I have resided
莫斯科大都会酒店317号套房
in Suite 317 of the Metropol Hotel.
原因
Why?
我的房子烧毁了
My house was burned down.
你的职业
Occupation?
绅士是不从事职业的
It is not the business of gentlemen to have occupations.
你似乎没意识到你处境的严重性
You do not seem to appreciate the gravity of your position.
不 恐怕我完全明白
No, I fear I understand it perfectly.
你在1914年春天离开俄国去了巴黎
You left Russia for Paris in the spring of 1914?
对 我记得当时苹果树好像正在开花
Yes, I remember apple blossom in the trees.
是的 十有八九是春天
In all likelihood, it was spring, yes.
我们更关心的是
What concerns us here
你在1918年返回了俄国
is your return in 1918.
你为什么在革命发生一年后就回来了
Why did you come back only a year after the Revolution?
你一定知道对于一个如你一样具有贵族身份的人来说
You must have understood the reception a man of your...
会遭受的特殊待遇
nobility would receive.
我想念这里的气候
I missed the climate.
是你创作了
Are you the author
这首1913年的诗
of this poem of 1913:
《我们的目标在哪里》吗
"Where Is Our Purpose Now? "
是你写的吗
Were you the author?
是我的作品 是的
It was attributed to me, yes.
很多人认为这首诗
Many consider this poem
是在号召大家发起革命行动
a call to revolutionary action.
我们很难将作者与一个
Hard for us to equate with a man
屈服于他所在阶级的腐败统治
who has clearly succumbed to the corruptions of his class
对俄国及其人民造成威胁的人等同起来
and now is a threat against Russia and her people.
我也是她的子民
I am one of her people.
你曾经是
You were.
我们本想把你关进监狱
It is our inclination to have you put against the wall.
但党内某些高层人士
But there are those within the senior ranks of the Party
因为你的诗
who, because of your poem,
将你视为改革英雄
count you among the heroes of the revolutionary cause.
所以 本委员会决定
Therefore, it is the judgment of this committee,
既然大都会酒店已被党接管
now the Metropol is under full Party control,
你被立即遣返至你所钟爱的那家酒店
that you be returned to the hotel of which you are so fond,
在那度过你的余生
where you will remain for the rest of your days.
请记住
And make no mistake,
你若再踏出大都会酒店一步
should you ever set foot outside of the Metropol again,
就会被枪毙
you will be shot.
先生们 我能找打回去的路
Gentlemen, I think I can find my own way.
走
Move.
莫斯科
1921年
那一天 伯爵以为他的生命结束了
That day, the Count thought his life was over,
但事实上才刚刚开始
but in truth it was only the beginning
but in truth it was only the beginning.
不仅是他 于我而言也是如此
lot just for him but for me, too.
接下来的几年里
And in the years that followed,
亚历山大·罗斯托夫伯爵将是我最重要的人
Count Alexander Rostov would come to mean the world to me.
殿下 我们不认为你可以
Your Excellency, we didn't think you'd- -
很高兴见到你 瓦西里
Good to see you, Vasily.
先生们 我的套房在三楼
My suite is on the third floor, gentlemen.
坐电梯还是走步梯
The lift or the stairs?
如果连上楼这种事都不能当机立断
How are we supposed to win on the field of battle
又如何能在战场上克敌制胜呢
if we can't decide between the lift and the stairs?
你上过战场吗
Have you ever been on the field of battle?
走楼梯吧
The stairs it is.
莫斯科大剧院的景色很美 不是吗
It's a beautiful view of the Bolshoi, isn't it?
这些东西都是你的吗
All these things are yours?
除了地板和床 是的
S- Save for the floorboards and the bed, yes.
我读过你的诗
I read your poem
你说这话的语气
The tone of your voice suggests
看来你不太喜欢这诗
that you are not a great admirer.
我很难相信
I found it hard to believe
这些诗句出自你这种人笔下
those words came from the mouth of a man like you.
这一切有很什么意义
What 1 the meaning of all this?
我是来带你到你房间去的
I'm here to show you to your quarters.
这里就是我的房间
es are my quarters.
这是什么地方
What is this place?
革命前 这些房间是
Before the Revolution, these rooms were
给酒店客人的仆人住的
for the servants of the hotel guests.
至少还有扇窗户
Well, it has a window at least.
我刚好能躺在这张床上
And I'll just about fit on this bed.
啊 我猜是升G调
Ah, G- sharp, I believe.
是的 这样就可以了 谢谢
Yes. This will do very nicely, thank you.
你的境况不允许你
Your diminished circumstances won't allow you
把所有的东西都搬进来
to keep all of your possessions.
不过我允许你带一些私人物品
But I will allow you to take a few personal items.
那其余的呢
And the rest?
将成为人民的财产
Becomes the property of the people.
我得补充一句 你酒店保险箱的钱财
I should add, we've liberated your currency
已被我们充公
from the hotel safe.
我们会提供食宿
Food and board will be provided.
你以及那些贵族们在莫斯科的生活已经结束了
Life for you and your kind is over in Moscow.
你永远都不能离开这个酒店
You must never leave this hotel.
你要是逃跑
If you do...
我会等着的
I'll be waiting.
抱歉
Apologies.
我还没问过你的名字
I never thought to ask your name.
我的名字与你无关
My name is not your concern.
谢谢你以最礼貌的方式
Well, thank you. You have carried out your duties
履行了你的职责
with the greatest courtesy available to you.
你把门打开
You open the door,
提起钟摆
raise the weights...
一周一次
...once a week.
务必记住 亚历山大
Without fail, Alexancer.
海伦娜
Helena.
第一天
晚上好 安德烈
Good evening, Andrey.
殿下 晚上好
Your Excellency, bonsoir.
我不确定你今晚是否要与我们一同用餐
I wasn't sure if you would be dining with us this evening.
他们承认会为我提供食宿
I was assured food and board.
我带您找张桌子
I'll show you to a table.
谢谢
Thank you.
蠢货
Imbeciles.
意式煎牛肉卷需要用意大利火腿包裹住小牛肉片
A saltimbocca requires veal wrapped in prosciutto.
意大利火腿呢 鼠尾草呢
Where is the prosciutto? Where is the sage?
主厨 没有意大利火腿 也没有鼠尾草
We have no prosciutto, Chef, or sage.
那就不是意式煎牛肉卷
Then this is not a saltimbocca!
-不 主厨  -只是没煮熟的小牛肉
No, Chef. - It is merely badly cooked veal.
对不起主厨 小牛肉用完了
Sorry, Chef, we're out of veal.
还用你说
Of course we're out of veal!
7号桌一份意式煎牛肉卷
A saltimbocca on table seven.
伯爵点的
For the Count.
伯爵
The Count?
他来了
Is he here?
-他在做什么  -我认为
·What's he doing? - I believe
他是在拒绝认输
he's refusing to be beaten.
一切都还满意吗 殿下
Everything to your satisfaction, Your Excellency?
这道意式煎牛肉卷
The saltimbocca...
是用鸡肉代替了小牛肉吗
...with chicken instead of veal?
而且没用意大利火腿
And instead of prosciutto,
是的是乌克兰火腿片
shaved Ukrainian ham?
至于鼠尾草
In place of the sage,
我承认我花了点时间辨别
and I must admit this took me a moment,
但我觉得是荨麻
but I think it's nettle.
现在有品位的男人很少见了
A man with taste is a rare thing these days.
是荨麻 殿下
Nettle it was, Your Excellency.
您的味觉品味依然出色 无与伦比
Your palate remains, uh, unsurpassed.
好极了 先生
Bravo, sir.
厉害
Bravo.
殿下
Your Excellency.
我没料到你会来
I- I didn't expect you.
雅罗斯拉夫 我愿意等你一会儿
Yaroslav, for you, I am happy to wait.
第四十七天
你好
Hello.
我喜欢你的胡子
I like your mustache.
我喜欢你的 呃 发型
I like your, uh, hair.
亚历山大·伊里奇
Alexander Ilyich?
真的是你吗
Is it really you?
尼古拉公爵 我亲爱的朋友 太好了
Prince Nikolai, my dear friend, it's so wonderful to- -
现在是尼古拉了
It's just Nikolai now.
你看起来气色不错
You're looking well.
你过得怎么样
How have you been?
我马上就来找你
I- I'll be with you in a moment.
全和我说说
Tell me everything.
我上次见你的时候
The last time I saw you, you were playing Bach
你在你祖母的晚宴上弹奏巴赫
at one of your grandmother's dinner parties.
我想我现在仍在晚宴上演奏巴赫
I guess I'm still playing Bach at dinner parties.
我大部分时间都会在这
I- I'll be here most weeks.
你母亲和妹妹都好吗
And your mother and sister are well?
她们在瑞士
They're in Switzerland.
哦对 我似乎听说了
Oh, yes, I think I had heard that.
你还住在以前的宫殿吗
Are you still, uh, living at the old palace?
他们已经接管了
They've taken it over.
不过 他们给我留了一间房
But, um, they let me keep a room.
至少我们还都好好的活着
Well, at least we have our health.
好了 我得走了
Well, I- I'd better get on.
当然 抱歉 我不是故意要拖着你
Of course. I'm sorry, I didn't mean to keep you.
也许我们可以在晚餐后
Perhaps w- we could have a drink at the bar
去酒吧喝一杯
after my dinner.
非常愿意
I'd like that very much.
尼古拉
Nikolai.
他们能夺走你的物质财产
They can take away your house or your rooms.
但他们无法剥夺你的品格和市质
They can't take away who you are.
我以为你在巴黎
I thought you were in Paris.
你到底为什么要回到这个疯人院
Why on earth did you return to this madhouse?
为了送我祖母安仝登上去英国的船
To get my grandmother safely on a ship to England.
奥德利斯 我们能再来一杯吗
Audrius, could we have the same again?
好的 殿下
Yes, Your Excellency.
谢谢
Thank you.
你妹妹的事我很遗憾
I was sorry to hear about your sister.
我们还在这做什么
What are we still doing here?
当我还是个小男孩时 这就是未来
When I was a young boy,
我父母去世不久后 我的祖母伯爵夫人
not long after my parents died, my grandmother the Countess
从邻近的庄园邀请了一个小男孩
invited a boy over from the neighboring estate.
她觉得这能让我高兴一点
She thought it might cheer me up.
大家叫他奥博连斯基
Obolensky he was called.
他在一次跳棋游戏中赢了我
He beat me at a game of draughts.
我接受不了
I didn't take it well.
我痛哭流涕 把棋子扔了满地
Tears were shed, pieces were scattered.
我甚至都骂人了
I might even have uttered a curse.
那天晚上
Later that evening,
她发现我仍然满腔怒火
she found me still full of rage.
她就说
And she said,
失败的滋味从来都不好受
"There's nothing pleasant to be said about losing,
那个奥博连斯基也确实是个讨厌鬼
and that Obolensky boy certainly is a pill,
但是萨沙 亲爱的 你为啥
but, Sasha, my dear, why on earth
要满足他这个快感呢
would you give him the satisfaction? "
奥博连斯基
Obolensky.
是弗拉基米尔·奥博连斯基 对吗
That's not Vladimir Obolensky, is it?
下奥博连斯基家族的吗
Of the Nizhny Obolenskys?
是 就是他
Yes, the very same.
你祖母说的对 他是个讨厌鬼
Your grandmother's correct, he is a pill.
他曾经是
He was.
他们把他活活烧死在家里了
They burned him alive in his house.
他们不会罢手的 萨沙
They won't stop, Sasha.
我认识一个人 他能
I know someone wh- who can...
提供文件确保安全过境
provide papers ensuring safe transit.
我们可以离开这个国家
We- we could leave the country.
除非我们在路上被入认出来
Unless we were recognized en route.
你得剃掉你的八字胡
Well, you'd have to clip your wings.
光这一点就够让我留下了
No, that alone is a good reason to stay.
萨沙 你怎么能开玩笑呢
Sasha, how can you joke?
因为如果我严肃看待这件事
Because if I take it seriously,
我可能会深陷绝望 找不到任何出路
I could fall into a dark despair I could find no way out from.
那些大门并未紧闭
There's no bars across the doors.
只要你离开酒店 我们就可以消失了
Once you're out of the hotel, we could disappear.
往东 往西
Go east, go west.
我们可以重新活过
We could start again.
以什么身份活
As who? As what?
这重要吗 我们会活下去
Does it matter? We would be alive.
这里仍是我的国家
This is still my country.
谢谢你
Thank you.
敬俄国
To Russia.
现在就我们俩了吗
Is it just us now?
是的 你很棒
Yes, you're so good.
为我的迟到抱歉
Apologies for my tardiness.
今天要剪什么发型 殿下
What will it be today, Your Excellency?
像往常一样 如果你愿意的话
Just the usual, if you'd be so kind.
我才是下一个
I was next.
我马上就来 先生
I will be with you in just a moment, sir.
我比他先到的
I was here before he was.
我周二中午12点
Oh, uh, I have a standing appointment
有固定预约
at 12 on a Tuesday.
请您稍安勿躁
If you would just please wait.
凭什么要我等 凭什么他排在我前面
Why should I? Why should he go before me?
我解释过了 我
Well, as I explained, I have a- -
他有固定预约
He has a standing appointment.
是我先来的
I was here first.
很快就能到您了
You'll have your appointment soon enough.
殿下
Your Excellency.
谢谢你
Thank you.
没必要 你家菜单我会背了
Oh, that won't be necessary. I know it by heart.
哦 您一定是顶楼的客人
Oh, you must be the guest from the top floor.
是的 很高兴认识你
Yes, delighted to make your acquaintance.
好 我来一份比目鱼柳
Well, yes, I will have the fillet of sole.
要来杯酒搭配鱼吗
Would you like a glass of wine with your fish?
苏特恩怎么样
A Sauternes, perhaps?
来瓶波德莱尔庄园的
Oh, I think a bottle of Chateau Baudelaire
也许更合适
might be more fitting.
当然可以
Of course.
谢谢你
Thank you.
-您的鱼 先生  -啊
Your fish, sir? - Ah.
看起来很好吃 谢谢
Ah, that looks delicious. Thank......
-它去哪儿了  -你说什么
Where did they go? - I beg your pardon?
-你的胡子  -哦 它
Your mustaches. Well, they, uh...
你真的是伯爵吗
·I...it...Is it true that you're a count?
-是的  -你认识公主吗
- It is. - Have you ever known a princess?
我认识好多公主呢
I have known many princesses.
做公主会不会很难
Was it terribly hard to be a princess?
特别难 尤其在我们光荣的革命之后更难
Terribly. Especially so since our glorious revolution.
这个好吃吗
Is that any good?
你不是有自己的午饭吗
Didn't you have a lunch of your own?
-在别的桌子上  -我不喜欢
·At a different table? - I didn't like it.
强烈推荐
With my compliments.
所以 公主的一天是怎么过的
So, how would a princess spend her day?
跟其他年轻女士一样
Like any young lady.
她会在早上上课
In the morning, she would have lessons.
下午去拜访朋友
In the afternoon, she would visit with friends.
午餐时会吃蔬菜
And at lunchtime, she would eat her vegetables.
我父亲说公主是被征服时代的
My father says that a princess personifies
堕落化身
the decadence of a vanquished era.
好吧 或许有那么几个
Well, perhaps a few.
但我向你保证 并不是所有公主
Not all, I can assure you.
别担心 我爸爸知道拖拉机运行的
Don't worry. Papa knows everything there is to know
一切原理
about the workings of a tractor,
但对公主的运行原理一无所知
but absolutely nothing about the workings of a princess.
你参加过决斗吗
Have you ever been in a duel?
不算参加过
Not exactly.
但我教父当过决斗助手
But my godfather was a second
还不止一次呢
on more than one occasion.
-助手  -当两位绅士
A second? - When two gentlemen
同意决斗后 他们会各自指派给副手
agree to duel, they each appoint seconds,
来制定交战规则的
lieutenants who settle upon the rules of engagement.
什么样的交战规则
What sort of rules of engagement?
时间 地点 使用什么武器
The time, the place, what weapons will be used.
假设用手枪要 走多少步之类
If it's pistols, how many paces.
我教父就参加过一场
One of the duels my godfather seconded
发生在这家酒店的决斗
sprang from a dispute that occurred
起因是海军上将和王子之间起了分歧
in this very hotel, between an admiral and a prince
有天晚上 他们的分歧在大厅中达到了顶峰
whose differences came to a head one night in the lobby.
他们爱上了同一个女人
Were they in love with the same woman?
我认为跟女人无关
I don't think a woman was involved.
切都跟女人有关
A woman is always involved.
好吧 我们先不管原因 当时
Yes, well, whatever the cause, at the time,
酒店由一个叫凯夫勒的人管理
the hotel was managed by a fellow named Keffler.
大家都知道 他办公室的一幅画后
And it was well known that he kept
常年放着一双古董手枪
a pair of antique pistols in his office behind a painting,
这样如果有人决定决斗
so that if a challenge was accepted,
就可以迅速召唤马车
carriages could be summoned,
各方也可以手握武器迅速离开
and parties could be whisked away, weapons in hand.
就在黎明前那段时间吗
In the hours before dawn?
去一个僻静的地方
To a secluded spot.
恐怕现实并没那么浪漫
The reality, I'm afraid, was not quite as romantic.
酒店经理想和你谈谈
The hotel manager would like to speak to you.
什么 我我能先吃完午餐吗
What? Might I finish my lunch first?
当然可以
Of course
谢谢你
Thank you.
谢谢你能过来
I appreciate your stopping by.
我的荣幸
It's my pleasure.
我注意到
It's been brought to my attention
某些员工 呃
that certain members of the staff, uh,
在称呼你的时候
when addressing you,
继续使用了一些
h- have continued to make use of certain...
夸张用语
um...amplifications.
是啊“殿下”之类的
Yeah, "Your Excellency, "and what have you.
啊 是的
Ah. Yes.
-我想是的  -嗯
- I suppose they have. - Hmm.
你知道 要是我说了算
Well, if it, you know, if it were up to me, um,
你懂的 那么自然
you know, naturally enough...
你知道的 这是自然而然的事
well, you know, goes without saying,
但是
but what with...
在他们那个年代 敬语是很优雅的
Uh, honorifics were elegant things in their day,
而现在 这些词似乎已失去了使用价值
but they, uh, they do seem to have outlived their usefulness.
时代需要改变 哈雷茨基先生
It is the business of times to change, Mr. Halecki.
绅士们也要跟着改变
And gentlemen to change with them.
很对
Quite.
我能问一下是谁告诉你的吗
Might I ask who brought this to your attention?
你知道他们为什么允许这家酒店
You know why they allow this hotel
继续开下去吗
to continue operating,
继续为客户服务吗
serving the clientele that it does?
以便他们监视每个人
So that everyone can be watched.
以便他们找到那些不忠于党的人
So they can find those disloyal to the party.
从革命以来就是如此
It's been that way since the Revolution.
情况只会越来越糟
It's only gonna get worse.
这家酒店是个危险的地方
This hotel is a dangerous place.
对你而言尤甚
Especially for you.
你看到了 瓦西里
As you can see, Vasily,
我正在跟我们一位客人
I'm in the middle of a conversation
谈话呢
with one of our guests.
向二位道歉
My apologies to you both,
但 我需要借一步说话
but if I could see you for a moment...
好吧
Very well.
说说吧
How do you propose
我们的计划是什么
we go about it?
我们得做好伪装
We'd have to wear a disguise.
我可以从住我家的
I- I can steal some coats
红军那里偷几件外套
from the Red Army soldiers that are staying at my home.
只要你自信点 没人会注意我们
You walk with confidence, no one will pay us any heed.
-你只是个平平无奇的布尔什维克士兵  -是的
Just another Bolshevik soldier. - Yes.
我会安排一辆车在外面等我们
Outside, I'll make sure there's a car waiting,
然后送我们去火车站
and from there, we'll go to the train station.
莫斯科到处都是红军士兵 但
There's Red Army soldiers all over Moscow, but...
会需要一些身份证明
these papers
我可以制作出来
that I can have drawn up,
应该能把我们送上火车
they should get us as far as the train.
然后我们就抛掉
From there, we lose
身上的红军徽章
our Red Army insignia
步行200英里 来到明斯克
and we walk the 200 miles to Minsk.
为我们的自由干杯
...and to our freedom.
那我们的财物呢
And- and our belongings?
不
No.
不能携带任何可能暴露身份的东西
We can't take anything with us that might give us away.
连海伦娜也不行吗
Not even Helena.
你需要多少钱
How much will you need?
你觉得这些够了吗
Do you think that might suffice?
-也许这样  -哦
Well, maybe...some...Oh.
谢谢你
·Thank you.
第六十五天
你要是走出去
Will they really shoot you
他们真的会开枪吗
if you go outside?
你怎么像个幽灵一样 来去无踪的
You appear and disappear like a spirit.
-你叫什么名字  -尼娜 库利科娃
What's your name? - Nina Kulikova.
亚历山大·伊里奇·罗斯托夫伯爵
Count Alexander Ilyich Rostov.
-你爸爸在哪儿  -他去工作了
Where is your father? - He's working.
他总是在工作
He's always working.
-你妈妈呢  -死了
And your mother? - Dead.
哦 真为你难过
Oh, I am sorry to hear that.
我在跟你一样大时 也失去了父亲和母亲
I lost both my father and my mother at a similar age.
说失去是不对的
People aren't lost.
他们是从我们身边夺走的
They're taken from us.
哦 小尼娜
Ah, little Nina,
我们要如何在这家酒店中熬过
how are we going to survive these endless days
这看不到头的日子呢
stuck in this hotel?
我找到个逃跑的办法
I've found a way to escape.
我有一把万能钥匙 能打开酒店的每一扇门
I have a passkey that opens every door in the hotel.
但你要牢记 这里房间套着房间
It's important to remember that there are rooms behind rooms
一扇门套着另一扇门
and doors behind doors.
来吧
Come on.
-你要带我们去哪  -你 一会儿就知道了
·Where are you taking us? - You'll see.
这是个销毁秘密信息
This is the perfect place
和非法情书的
to destroy secret messages
完美之地
and illicit love letters.
你真的收到过非法情书吗 伯爵
You do receive illicit love letters, Count?
那当然
Most certainly.
还有好多
There's more.
-我觉得还是不要  -别这么老顽固
- I'm not sure we should- - - Don't be such a fuddy- duddy.
从这里我们能监视舞厅
Look, we can spy on the ballroom.
来吧
Come on.
拉这根杆 整个舞厅就会
If you pull this lever, it throws the ballroom
陷入完全黑暗
into complete darkness.
这边走
This way.
以前总是她
Oh, she's the maid who used
为我换床单
to change my sheets.
-闭上眼睛 闭上眼睛  -她叫玛丽娜
...eyes closed, eyes closed. Her name's Marina.
他每天都会把剩饭收集起来
Every day she collects leftover food,
为她儿子做一顿大餐
to make a feast for her little boy.
他儿子叫亚夏
His name's Yasha.
这些都是酒店客人留下的
These are all the novels and travel guides
小说和旅游指南
hotel guests leave behind.
这是我教父最喜欢的椅子
This was my godfather's favorite chair.
这都是些老物件而已
They're just things.
这东西承载了我的所有记忆
AII my memories exist within them.
从这儿穿过来
Through here.
来啊 我还有东西给你看
Come on, there's more I have to show you.
来吧
Come on.
看
Look.
我不记得这里放过这些 这是要干什么
I didn't know this was here. What's all this for?
爸爸说是一些重要的政府工作
Papa says some government work
不能搬进克里姆林宫的那种
is too important even for the Kremlin.
来 我们走
Come on, let's go.
藏起来
Hide.
我们还要抓到多少个
How many do we have
-才能交差  -早上14个
to get through tomorrow? - Uh, 14 in the morning
-下午12点  -只有12个
and 12 in the afternoon. - Only 12?
我们已经收集了一些证据
That we have gathered evidence against.
证据 你需要什么证据
Evidence? What evidence do you need?
给我人名 我来找罪行
Give me a man and I will find a crime.
再给我五个人名都行
Five more names.
第六十七天
他们在抓更多的人
They're rounding more people up,
把他们送上审判席
putting them on trial.
对他们而言 是否真的犯罪
It doesn't matter to them whether a crime
并不重要
has been committed or not.
那我们就更该离开了
That's all the more reason for us to go.
是你该离开
For you to go.
抓紧时间吧 趁你还有机会
And quickly, while you still have a chance.
我在名单上看到了你名字
I saw your name on a list.
我今天去拿身份证明了
I picked up the papers today.
再过几个星期 一切就会就绪
A few more weeks and everything will be in place for our escape.
我们可等不了几个星期 估计就在这几天了
We don't have a few more weeks, it could be days.
几个小时
Hours.
你必须马上走
You have to leave now.
但你得跟我走
But you have to come with me.
我不能
I can't.
与之前不走的原因一模一样
For the same reason I couldn't leave before.
为了海伦娜
Helena?
是的
Yes.
或许我用不着我告诉你
There's no use me telling you that...
她也会希望你过好自己的生活
she'd want you to live your life.
也许我不配
Perhaps I don't deserve to.
你要是改变了主意
You ever change your mind.
这个能让你安全通过
...these will get you safe passage.
你是个真正的朋友
You are a true friend.
但是 不用了
But no.
现在 你今晚必须走了
Now, you must go. Tonight.
我会的
I will.
等我在俄罗斯的的土地上 最后弹一遍拉赫玛尼诺夫就走
After I've played Rachmaninoff on Russian soil one last time.
你知道吗 尼娜
And would you know, Nina,
尼古拉·彼得罗夫是现实中的王子
Nikolai Petrov is a real- life prince?
没错
Yes.
他父亲是一位著名将军
His father was a famous general,
可他一点也没继承骁勇善战的基因
but fighting wasn't in his blood.
他最大的爱好是音乐
His one great love is music.
据说从他三岁起
And they say that since he was three years old,
他拿着小提琴的时间比不拿还要长
he spent more time with a violin in his hand than without.
尼古拉
Nikolai.
Nikolai!
尼古拉
你的朋友跟几个我们
Your friend did some business
一直在监视的人做了交易
with an element we've been watching.
我很好奇 他怎么会需要两套旅行证件
I'm curious as to why he needed two sets of travel documents.
多年之后 伯爵告诉我
Years later, the Count would tell me
他真希望自己那晚再勇敢一些
that he wished he'd had the courage to do more.
而事实是 假如那晚他离开酒店
In truth, had he left the hotel that night,
几秒钟后 他就会横尸街头
he would have died on the pavement a few seconds later.
我也不会活到现在 把这个故事讲给你
And I would not be alive to tell this tale.